Finding Aid for Morley Winograd Papers, 1973-1983
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Morley Winograd Papers 1973-1983, 1976-1979
Winograd, Morley, 1942-
1 linear feet
921091 Aa 2
Democratic Party official, chairman of the Michigan Democratic Party from 1973 to 1979, president of the Association of State Democratic Chairs from 1979 to 1980, and chairman of the Commission on Presidential Nomination and Party Structure from 1973 to 1978. Committee work files and reports relating to his various political appointments.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Mr. Winograd in 1992 (Donor no. 7910 ).
The collection is open to research.
Born into a relatively wealthy family from Detroit (his father owned a chain of haberdashery stores) on November 12, 1942, Winograd graduated from the University of Michigan in 1963 with a bachelor's in business administration. He first became involved in local politics in Troy, Oakland County in the late 1960s and then jumped to state politics when he won the election for chairman of the state Democratic Party in 1973. He moved into national politics when he was elected secretary of the Democratic National Committee's (DNC) Association of State Democratic Chairs (ASDC) in 1975.
In the mid-1970s to the early 1980s, he became a rising force in the Democratic Party, both in Michigan and nationally. He served as chairman of the Michigan Democratic Party from 1973 to 1979 and was elected president of the Association of State Democratic Chairs (ASDC) from 1979 to 1980. Winograd was also active in the Democratic National Committee (DNC), serving as the appointed chairman of the Commission on Presidential Nomination and Party Structure from 1975 to 1978.
Widely recognized as a master organizer and facilitator in the political process, Winograd nevertheless began to fall into disfavor in Michigan by 1978 until 1980, when his own personal views were questioned, primarily by African-American Democrats, most notably Detroit Mayor Coleman Young, who charged Winograd with racism. He resigned as chairperson of the Michigan Democratic Party in 1979 and was not re-elected as president of the ASDC in 1980. Winograd was appointed by Governor James Blanchard to the Michigan Commission on the Bicentennial of the United States Constitution in 1986 and served as chairman from 1988 to 1991.
There are four series in this collection, each one relating to a different political activity in Morley Winograd's life: Association for Democratic State Chairs (ASDC); Democratic National Committee, Delegate Selection records; Commission on Presidential Nomination and Party Structure; and Michigan Democratic Party.
Subjects:
Democratic Party (Mich.); Democratic Party (U.S.); Democratic Party (U.S.). Commission on Presidential Nomination.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Michigan--Politics and government--1981-1990.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Winograd, Morley.
- Association for Democratic State Chairs (ASDC)
  The Association for Democratic State Chairs series documents the group's work and concerns during Winograd's tenure as president. Although not extensive, the materials do show the ASDC's interest in party building and the federal election process. The materials on DEMPAC represent the work of a coalition between the ASDC, DNC, and the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee (DCCC), formed in 1980 "to block Republican efforts to control the reapportionment process in 1982 by winning state legislatures in 1980." (Quote from DEMPAC folder).
  - Agendas and Minutes 1979-1980, undated (Box 1)
  - Budgets 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Carter/Kennedy Nomination 1980 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1979 (Box 1)
  - DEMPAC 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Memos 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous undated (Box 1)
  - News Releases 1979 (Box 1)
  - Task Forces
    - Dollars for Dems 1979 (Box 1)
    - Federal Election Campaign (F.E.C.) 1979, undated (Box 1)
    - Party Building 1979 (Box 1)
  - Testimonies before Congress 1979 (Box 1)
- Democratic National Committee, Delegate Selection
  The Democratic National Committee Delegate Selection series shows Winograd's push for changes in the DNC's delegate selection rules. Although Wiongrad's proposals were ultimately unsuccessful, the materials nevertheless illustrate how members could try to initiate change within the DNC.
  - Correspondence 1973, 1976, 1981-1983, undated (Box 1)
  - Reports 1981, undated (Box 1)
- Commission on Presidential Nomination and Party Structure
  The Commission on Presidential Nomination and Party Structure series dominates the collection in both breadth and depth. It spans from 1975, when Winograd was appointed chairman, to 1978 when the final report was presented. It is comprised of administrative and background materials the Commission used in their efforts to revise the presidential primary system. Of these, the complete set of transcripts of the September 9, 1977 full Commission meeting, the reports (administrative and background), and the surveys (two of which show the results) are especially informative.
  The final product of the Commission was a report entitled, "Openness, Participation and Party Building: Reforms for a Stronger Democratic Party." To understand the evolution of, and responses to this document, consult the Final Results: Commission Reports and Related section.
  - Administrative
    - Background (including history) 1976-1978, undated (Box 1)
    - Agendas 1976-1978 (Box 1)
    - Budget (proposed) 1977 (Box 1)
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1976-1978 (Box 1)
    - Full Commission Meetings
      - Minutes and Summaries June 24, 1977 (Box 1)
      - Transcripts September 9, 1977, 4 volumes (Box 1)
    - Memos 1975, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - Reports (Administrative and Background)
      - Delegate Selection undated (Box 1)
      - DNC Executive Committee Recommendations 1978 (Box 1)
      - The 1976 Presidential Primaries, 1977 (Box 1)
      - Presidential Primaries 1976, undated (Box 1)
      - State Hearings 1977, undated (Box 1)
      - Weekly Reports 1977 (Box 1)
    - Statements before Commission undated (Box 1)
    - Surveys undated (Box 1)
    - Task Forces
      - Background undated (Box 1)
      - Pre-Delegate Selection 1977, undated (Box 1)
      - Implementation of Delegate Selection undated (Box 1)
      - Post Delegate Selection 1977, undated (Box 1)
  - Final Results: Commission Reports and Related (including drafts)
    - Interim Report 1976 (Box 1)
    - Preliminary Report 1977 (Box 1)
    - Drafting Committee (proposed changes to report) undated (Box 1)
    - Final Report: "Openness, Participation and Party Building: Reforms for a Stronger Democratic Party," 1978 (Box 1)
    - Reactions to Commission's Reports 1976-1978, undated (Box 1)
    - Commission as it relates to Michigan (Winograd's summary) undated (Box 1)
- Michigan Democratic Party
  The Michigan Democratic Party series documents two major topics: Winograd's campaigns for chairman and his conflicts regarding race with the African-American community and Mayor Coleman Young in 1978 and 1980 respectively. For both topics, the clippings (not arranged in any particular order) are the most illuminating of the materials.
  - Chairmanship Campaign
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and Miscellaneous 1973, 1975-1979, undated (Box 1)
  - Clippings
    - Black Caucus (Box 1)
    - Dispute with Mayor Coleman Young (re: charge of racism) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1973-1974, 1977-1978, 1982, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous undated (Box 1)